<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Vedhavyas Singareddi</title>
    <link>http://vedhavyas.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Vedhavyas Singareddi</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://vedhavyas.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Did You Know: Chapter 2</title>
      <link>http://vedhavyas.com/posts/did-you-know-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://vedhavyas.com/posts/did-you-know-2/</guid>
      <description>In the Soviet era Russia your land could be transferred to others by the state and hence was not private property. The .COM TLD was one of the first created in 1985 Root name servers  There are 13 root name server around the world operated by 12 independent organisations Each name server starts with [name].root-servers.net, with name replaced with any of chars including [a-m] Even though there are 13 root name servers, each of the 13 organisations that maintain these servers deploys multiple physical servers around the globe This basically means, there is load balancer for each root name server before all the physical servers deployed in different locations Infrastructure TLDs: .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How DNS Works</title>
      <link>http://vedhavyas.com/posts/how-dns-works/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://vedhavyas.com/posts/how-dns-works/</guid>
      <description>Note: If you find any issues in the post, let me know in the comments section
This is a short post how DNS works. Prefer more comical learning, then go here - https://howdns.works/
So what happens when you type in a website address? User entered address https://vedhavyas.com. Browser needs to resolve this address to an public IP address.
 Browser cache  Browser check its local cache for an IP address that maps to given website address If found, call the IP address to serve the request.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Did You Know: Chapter 1</title>
      <link>http://vedhavyas.com/posts/did-you-know-chapter-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://vedhavyas.com/posts/did-you-know-chapter-1/</guid>
      <description>The first internetwork message sent was “lo”, first 2 letters in “login”, since the receiving system crashed after “lo”. Circuit Switching Vs Packet Switching  Circuit Switching  The data is transferred in 3 phases  Connection established Data Transfer Connection Released  Each data unit knows the entire path since the path the connection is explicitly established for this transfer Hence, this is very reliable The data unit is processed at the Receiving end The delay between data unit is uniform But wastage of lots of resources  Packet Switching  Data is transferred directly Packet only know the end destination but the intermediate nodes may change Its not very reliable Data is processed at intermediate nodes as well as destination node The delay between data units is not uniform But very less resource wastage   In packet switching, due to less reliability of the transfer, we end up doing acknowledgements to and fro.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regular Expressions</title>
      <link>http://vedhavyas.com/posts/regex/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://vedhavyas.com/posts/regex/</guid>
      <description>Note: If you find any issues in the post, do let me know in the comments section.
Regular Expressions  It is not a Programming language Everything is a character  Character classes dot class  . matches every character except line breaks.  match Any  [\s\S] matches every character including line breaks.  word  \w matches low ascii characters - alphanumeric and underscore equivalent to [a-zA-Z0-9_]  not word  \W matches anything other than a word equivalent to [^a-zA-Z0-9_]  digit  \d matches any digit from 0 to 9 equivalent to [0-9]  not digit  \D matches any character other than digit equivalent to [^0-9]  space  \s matches spaces, tabs, line breaks  not space  \S matches any other than space, tabs, line breaks  character set  [] matches any character in the set  example  expression: [aeiou]</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>